<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of ... Lady Mary, daughter to Ferdinando, late Earl of Huntingdon, and wife to William Jolife of Caverswell-castle in the county of Stafford, Esq. ... Decemb. xii, 1678 by Samuel Willes ...</title>
            <author>Willes, Samuel, 1611-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2305</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12444879</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12444879</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62197</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62197)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 301:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of ... Lady Mary, daughter to Ferdinando, late Earl of Huntingdon, and wife to William Jolife of Caverswell-castle in the county of Stafford, Esq. ... Decemb. xii, 1678 by Samuel Willes ...</title>
                  <author>Willes, Samuel, 1611-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for John Baker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jolliffe, Mary, --  Lady, d. 1678.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62197:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62197:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D At the Funeral of the Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> The Lady MARY, Daughter to <hi>Ferdinando</hi> late Earl of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> AND Wife to WILLIAM JOLIFE of <hi>Caverſwell</hi>-Caſtle in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> Eſq; At <hi>Aſhby-De-la-Zouch, Decemb.</hi> xii. 1678.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL WILLES,</hi> M. A. and Preacher at <hi>All-hallows</hi> in <hi>Derby.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Guil. Sill.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>April 12. 1679.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>John Baker,</hi> at the three Pigeons in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62197:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62197:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> THEOPHILUS Earl of Huntingdon.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>HAD Your Lordſhip commanded to this performance a Perſon of Sufficiencies, in any tolerable meaſure, ſuitable to the occaſion of it, You had found your ſelf better ſerved. And more right had been done to the Memory of your Noble Siſter, than the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poor Accounts of her can amount unto; which have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to commend them, but that (as far as they reach) they are true. Nor can I ſuffer imputation from any that knew this Excellent Lady, in any degree of intimacy, but only in having ſpoken ſo extreme defectively, and in ſo mean terms, concerning her. And yet, perhaps, I have ſaid enough to provoke the Envy of ſome others, who love not to hear of any Commendations but what are aſcribed to themſelves. To whom I ſhall only ſuggest a return of Dr.</hi> Donne's <hi>upon a not much different occaſion,</hi> Let any Lady make <note place="margin">Donnes <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. p.</hi> 253.</note> her ſelf fit for thoſe Praiſes, and they ſhall be hers.
<pb facs="tcp:62197:3"/> 
               <hi>And I heartily wiſh I had been able ſo to have repreſented this Illuſtrious Example (for it needed no Ornament but bare Narration) as to excite in others a vertuous Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I am ſenſible how ſhort I have fallen of the Dignity of my Subject. And had not your Lordſhip's very great and very juſt Affection to this Incomparable Lady ſomewhat impoſed upon your Accurate Judgment, your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip would never have ſent this Sermon to the Preſs. But though it muſt abide (as far better things daily do) all licenſe of cenſure; yet if any thing therein ſhall in the leaſt aſsiſt any good Soul in true</hi> Devotion, <hi>I ſhall eſteem the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation abundantly recompenſed to,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, Samuel Willes.</signed>
               <dateline>DERBY, <date>Apr 6. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62197:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>S. LUKE XX. 36.</bibl>
               <q>Neither can they die any more; for they are equal unto the Angles, and are the Children of God, being the Children of the Reſurrection.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE are our Saviour's words, in anſwer to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Atheiſts, the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees,</hi> who (among their other Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) deni'd there was any Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead. Theſe Men put a Caſe to our Saviour; with a captious and malicious purpoſe, to enſnare him in ſuch Abſurdities, as they vainly conceiv'd his Anſwer would betray him to. The Caſe was this: A Woman in the courſe of her life had ſeven Husbands ſucceſſively, and ſurvived them all. Now (ſuppoſing a Reſurrection of the Dead) to which of the ſeven ſhall this Woman ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain, when ſhe and they riſe again? For ſhe was not more one Man's Wife, than ſhe was another's: all muſt have her then, or none. This was their Queſtion: to which our Lord makes this return, That the Woman at the Reſurrection, could be claim'd by none of all her Husbands: For though <hi>the Children of this World marry, and are given in Marriage,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 20. 34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>they, which ſhall be accounted worthy to obtain that World, and</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62197:4"/> 
               <hi>the Reſurrection from the dead, neither marry, nor are given in Marriage.</hi> None of the ends for which that ſtate was ordained, having any place there. There being no need of Procreation, and multiplying and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing Mankind; nor of any remedy againſt Sin; nor of any ſuch help and comfort, which that relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on affords here.</p>
            <p>There is no need of Procreation. <hi>For the Children of the Reſurrection cannot die any more.</hi> And where there is no Death, there is no want of ſuch means to repair the ruines of Mortality. Thoſe that are to live for ever, cannot need a ſucceſſion to fill their room after them, and to continue their kind. Neither is there any need of a remedy againſt Sin: For they are <hi>equal unto the Angles;</hi> perfectly free from all fleſhly inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, having glorified Bodies, utterly uncapable of thoſe low deſires. They become pure and ſpiritual by the Reſurrection, as the Angles are by Nature. Nor is there (in the World to come) the leaſt need of that ſociety, help and comfort, which the relation of Marriage affords here. For they are <hi>the Children of God;</hi> like unto him, in a nearer and more exact reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, than the greateſt Grace can make us here. The Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be inſtated in ſo full and perfect Happineſs and Glory, as ſhall render all Aſſiſtances of the deareſt and moſt helpful Relation perfectly needleſs. What uſe can there be of ſuch help and ſuccour in that ſtate, where nothing can be wanting?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62197:4"/>
            <p>In this manner does our bleſſed Lord refute this idle Cavil of the <hi>Sadducees.</hi> But this is not all: For he was pleaſed here (as elſewhere in the holy Goſpel) to take occaſion, from a ſpiteful and captious Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to declare and aſſert a great and neceſſary Truth; making ſuch a Reply, as might at once ſilence their Malice, and inform their Underſtanding. And what was deliver'd for the conviction of thoſe Gainſayers, is equally uſeful for the comfort of all Believers. And accordingly the Text inſtructs us, in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable inſtances, what ſhall be the ſtate of Holy Men at the Reſurrection. Such Men being <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Reſurrection;</hi> that is to ſay, partakers of it, (for ſo the phraſe imports) ſuch as are <hi>accounted worthy to obtain the World to come, and the Reſurrection from the Dead;</hi> Of theſe happy Perſons our Lord affirms three things, as eminent parts of their Felicity and Glory.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Their perfect Immortality, <hi>They can die no more.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. Their ſimilitude to the Angles, <hi>They are equal to them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. Their reſemblance even to God himſelf; They are <hi>the Children of God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I. Their perfect Immortality, <hi>They cannot die any more.</hi> The perfection of heavenly Glory is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of it, and the impoſſibility of ever loſing it.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62197:5"/> Otherwiſe, fear of deprivation would imbitter even that ineffable ſtate. <hi>And the fulneſs of Joy which is in God's Preſence,</hi> would be defective, were not <hi>thoſe Pleaſures [for evermore.]</hi> But they are ſuch, as admit no Interruption, and fear no Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Alas! we finde here, that Life, though in the beſt and moſt deſired enjoyments and ſatisfactions of it, has a bitter allay from the thoughts of Death. Unprepared Men tremble at it: and even the Beſt and moſt Holy are, upon remembrance of Death, ſtricken into Fear and Apprehenſion. Nor do we dread Death only in contemplation of the Victory it muſt have over our Selves, but over our Friends too; the dear Companions and Pledges of our Love; the Objects of our tendereſt Affection; the moſt kind and indulgent Husband, the moſt obliging and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wife, the moſt hopeful and promiſing Child, the moſt provident and wiſe Father, the moſt uſeful and faithful Friend, <hi>(who is as our own Soul:)</hi> Theſe <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 6</note> are ſnatcht from us by Death, and theſe dear enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments render us the wider marks for miſery and for ſorrow. And it cannot but ſhake us in our higheſt ſatisfactions, to conſider how near we ſtand (for ought we know) to the extremeſt loſs and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            <p>But O how happy will that ſtate be, wherein our Joys ſhall be compleat and perfect; having in them not any, the leaſt mixture of ſorrow or miſery. In
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62197:5"/> all worldly delights, either Defect, or Satiety, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation, or all of them are great and perpetual di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhings of our content; But none of them have any place in Heaven. There our deſires ſhall be more fully ſatisfied, than 'tis poſſible for us now to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend: Our capacities of pleaſure ſhall be ſutable to thoſe eternal joys; and no poſſibility of ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturbed in thoſe unſpeakable enjoyments, or deprived of them. There we ſhall live in the Extaſies and Raptures of glorified Communion with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, and Martyrs, and all the vertuous and pious Souls, in the Church Triumphant. And this without the abatements of Ignorance, Envy, or any of thoſe paſſions, which moleſt our correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies here. There the <hi>Spirits of all juſt men ſhall be made perfect.</hi> The glorious Society ſhall be for ever united in deareſt Love: ſwallowed up in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of God, and of all his wondrous benefits to the ſons of men, and in returning thoſe praiſes and ſervices, which our exalted ſouls ſhall then be able to perform. And this bleſſed concourſe ſhall be eternal. Every Member in that glorified Aſſembly being out of all poſſibility of defection or end. They <hi>cannot die any more.</hi> Death can never find entrance. The ſecurity of that Happineſs ſhall be the Crown of it. That Life muſt be eternal: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'tis not poſſible they ſhould die any more.</p>
            <p>And is it not moſt juſt and reaſonable, that our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62197:6"/> Solicitude and Labour to attain this eternal Life, ſhould be proportionate to the dignity and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of it? Who would not part with all the Honours and Advancements, with all the Riches and Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the gilded follies and vanities of this World, rather than fall ſhort of a part in this Heavenly Kingdom? We labour and toil, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and comply, and do any thing, and ſuffer every thing, for the preſervation and continuance of a mortal and periſhing Life, howſoever embit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd to us; but (Good God!) how little and how coldly are our Thoughts employ'd to make ſure of everlaſting Life? We direct, it may be, ſome faint wiſhes that way, now and then: The fragments of our time perhaps may be employ'd a little that way too. And 'tis poſſible that ſome publick Conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſome perſonal Fear may conſtrain and force in us ſome, extraordinary applications towards Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for a time. But the motion is artificial only, and ceaſes when the weights are taken off. Then we return to our former indifferency, and all the negligences of delay. We conclude it time enough to think of another World, when we have ſerved our turns in this. Religion is a fit employment for melancholy Old-age; when the Blood grows chill and languid, the Face wrinkled, when the Appetites to Pleaſure and Folly forſake us, when we come to the Staff, and to the Couch, and grow burdenſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62197:6"/> to our ſelves, and to others; when theſe evil Days are come, Devotion may be a proper entertainment. Till then, 'tis but a tormenting us before our time, an impoſing upon the pleaſure and gaity of Life.</p>
            <p>But certainly a Man muſt have very mean and vile thoughts of Eternal Life, that does not eſteem it worthy of more early and vigorous endeavours to gain it: but would embrace it only (when he ſees he muſt depart from hence) as an expedient to ſave him from Eternal Miſeries. That Man alone is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attain the Joys above, who ſeeks firſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, who makes it the great deſign and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of his whole Life, and who contains all inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our things in their due diſtance and ſubordination. Let us therefore be perſuaded to call in all our ſtragling Affections, and fix and employ all the powers of our Souls to the gaining this happy ſtate of Immortality; where we ſhall find all our labours and pains, our ſelf-denials and ſufferings abundantly recompenced. For there we ſhall have Knowledg without Miſtake: Poſſeſſions without fading: Riches without care or loſs: Honour without Envy. There ſhall be no Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, nor no Sins: No more ſtriving between the Fleſh and Spirit: Our Souls ſhall never deſire to have more, nor fear to have leſs: There we ſhall enjoy all that our Hearts can wiſh, and never grow weary of our wiſhes. There we ſhall poſſeſs all that we deſire: and ſtill deſire the very things we poſſeſs. In a word,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62197:7"/> we ſhall be raviſh'd in the beholding God, ſatisfy'd in the enjoying him, and all this without fear of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him. We ſhall dwell with the Eternal God in Life Eternal.</p>
            <p>II. The Children of the Reſurrection have a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude to the bleſſed Angels. <hi>They are equal unto the Angels.</hi> Not in all points. Different Natures muſt have different Proprieties. Put if the Angels have advantage in ſome Inſtances, we ſhall have it in others. And particularly in the endearment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. They reverence Jeſus Chriſt as God: we, as a Saviour alſo. They adore, we love him. His Glory affects them, his Mercy us. They deſire to <hi>look into that Myſtery,</hi> which we enjoy. Our fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is their great Contemplation. Their employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Heb. 1. laſt.</note> here (in part) is to <hi>miniſter for them, who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation:</hi> and in Heaven, our Salvation fills them with wonder and extaſy. Lord, what is Man, that thou art ſo mindful of him! A poor mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinful Wretch, that thou ſhouldſt ſo regard him! But ſo ſhall it be with the Man, whom the King of Heaven delighteth to Honour. Oh the wonders of Divine Love! The miracles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption! Duſt and Aſhes, like unto the Angels. Like unto them in Glory: In fitneſs to ſerve God, and in capacity of enjoying him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Like unto the Angels in Glory. And what their Glory is, and what ours ſhall be, when we are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62197:7"/> made like unto them, is impoſſible to be deſcribed any further, than the holy Scriptures do afford us ſome intimations of it. The Goſpel <hi>(Mat. 28. 3.)</hi> repreſents the Angels appearance at the Sepulchre in terms more ſuited to our comprehenſions, than to his Glory: Yet 'tis ſaid, <hi>His Countenance was like Lightning, and his Rayment white as Snow:</hi> A glorious and amazing Luſtre did encompaſs him: which made <note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> the Guards <hi>ſhake, and become as dead Men.</hi> But as great as it was, this was ſtill a Glory reſtrain'd, ſuch as the Eyes of Men might endure to look upon. For this Angel ſpake to the holy Women, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> 
               <hi>departed with fear and with great joy.</hi> Their fear was not ſo great at his Preſence, as to extinguiſh their joy at his Meſſage. But when the Angels Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is without check and limitation, in the full ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Heavenly Attendance: then certainly 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond expreſſion. Such ſhall be the Glory of the Children of the Reſurrection. <hi>It is ſown in Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <note place="margin">Cor. 15. 42.</note> it is raiſed in Glory,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul.</hi> Andthus Mat. 13. 43. <hi>Then ſhall the Righteous ſhine forth as the Sun, in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> again, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 21. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall change our vile Body, that it may be faſhioned like unto his Glorious Body.</hi> All manner of imperfection ſhall be excluded, and ſuch a Glory ſhall ſucceed it, as may render us fitInhabitants for Heaven, and partakers of the Bliſs of it. But 'tis not for us as yet to comprehend it:<hi> For it is does not yet appear what we ſhall be.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62197:8"/>2. The Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be like unto the Angels, in fitneſe to ſerve God. Whilſt we are here in the Fleſh, the Soul is diſadvantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly lodg'd. Corruption within, and Temptation without are great Impediments, ſo that we cannot attend to Service of God without troubleſome diſtractions. When our Devotion is at the higheſt, it ſuffers exceedingly from our Ignorance and Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Spirit is held down by the Fleſh; and we are ſo loaded with the impediments of Nature, that we difficultly attain any tollerable elevation of Soul, and more difficultly preſerve it. But in Heaven we ſhall be deliver'd from all Infirmities of the Fleſh, and ſerve and glorifie our God, as Angels do: with underſtanding, readineſe, vigour, ſpeed, unity, and all other perfections of Obedience. The <hi>Woman ofTekoah,</hi> when ſhe would celebrate the Wiſdom of <hi>David,</hi> went as high as ſhe could in her Compariſon:<hi>My Lord is Wiſe</hi> (faith ſhe) <hi>according to the Wiſdom of <note place="margin">2 Sam. 14. 20.</note> an Angel of God.</hi> The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays of Angels, that <hi>They excel in ſtrength, and do his Commandments, heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto the voice of his Word,</hi> Pſal. 103. 20. Divers other Excellencies does the holy Scripture aſcribe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe Heavenly Miniſters; which nevertheleſs do not give them greater Abilities to do ſervice to God, than we ſhall enjoy in a glorifi'd Eſtate. And O how happy will that Condition be, when ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from all Luſts and Paſſions, all Sin and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62197:8"/> we ſhall be exalted to Powers and Abilities of ſerving the Divine Majeſty, as his mighty Angels do! Here our Praiſes and Adorations are faint and cold: There they ſhall be offer'd in all the Raptures of a glorified Soul. Here with infinite Toil we gain a defective Knowledge: There we ſhall have it in full meaſure. All the ſecrets of Providence and of Nature (ſo far at leaſt as that Knowledge is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that place ) ſhall be manifeſted to our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Here we perform our Duties in a poor ſcanty faſhion, ſtriving perpetually with the indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and reluctancies of Nature: There we ſhall readily and perfectly obey the Will of God. Thoſe little ſparks of Divine Fire, which ſometimes have toucht our Souls, in the exerciſes of Devotion, ſhall then riſe to a mighty flame. The enlarged Soul will then pay a Service, ſuitable to the God it adores,and to the Preſence and Society in which it abides: Angels and Saints joyning in full Chore to ſing Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the Enternal God for evermore. United Love, perfect Service, and unſpeakable Joy ſhall be for ever in that <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi> And none of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Diſtinctions, Separations, and uncharitable Diviſions that wound and deform our Communion here, ſhall have any room in that bleſſed Aſſembly. But an univerſal conſent ſhall be for ever amongſt the Members of that glorious Society; all uniting in the moſt joyful Adorations of the Deity. And as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62197:9"/> as we ſhall then be like unto the Angels, in our fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſerve God; ſo</p>
            <p n="3">3. In our Capacities to enjoy him. <hi>Now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly, but then Face to Face,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. 12. 'Tis but a Glimps here, a full Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Heaven. In this World the Imbecillity of Nature cannot ſuſtain any great diſcovery of God. Hereafter we ſhall be made capable of the beatific Viſion: We ſhall ſee God, and ſee him as he is: Not as now, under the vail of a Similitude; (for all that we know of him here, is taught us by reſemblances) but we ſhall receive clear apprehenſions of him. We ſhall then have a diſtinct knowledg of that Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, which God has made appear ſo eminently in all his Works. In ſhort, all that the Angles do enjoy of God ſhall be vouchſafed to us alſo; a full participation of ſupreme Felicity.</p>
            <p>If at our return from the public Service of God at Church; if after the Sacrament devoutly received, if after the fervent performance of the duties of our Cloſet, we have found a warmth in our Hearts, our Souls ſtrangely delighted and raiſed to an unuſual degree of Satisfaction; if the Crums, that fall from the Table do afford us ſo great a delight, what ſhall we feel, when we come to <hi>ſit down in the Kingdom of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 13. 19.</note> at the Heavenly Feaſt of everlaſting Joys and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? It was one of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s three Wiſhes, to have ſeen Jeſus Chriſt in the Fleſh: This would have
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62197:9"/> been in the humility and abaſement of His Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What muſt it be to behold him in all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of his Kingdom? And to enjoy him there, to adore him as God, to love him as a Redeemer; to be united to him the Head of all the Members in the Church Triumphant? Certainly, in that ſtate, where the Soul ſhall be exalted to her utmoſt poſſibilities, one of its greateſt entertainments will be the clear diſcerning and full comprehenſion of the Love of the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in doing and ſuffering ſo much for us Men, and for our Salvation. And this will fill us with ſuch ardency of Love to him, as ſhall tranſport us with unexpreſſible Joy and And what can we imagin more conducing to full and perfect Bleſſedneſs, than to underſtand the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Myſteries of Divine Love, and to be able to make our returns of Love in ſo high and noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. If the Transfiguration did ſo raviſh Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as to make him cry out, Maſter, it is good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here; what muſt it be, when our Capacities ſhall be enlarg'd ſo, as to recive and enjoy the full Tide, the mighty Torrent of Divine Majeſty and Glory?</p>
            <p>It is no wonder (ſince 'every common thing baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles the largeſt Underſtanding) that here, we have ſuch poor and narrow conceptions of God. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching find out God? Canſt thou find out the Almighty unto Perfection?</hi> ſays <hi>Zophar,</hi> Job 11. 7. Should God diſcover himſelf to us in any meaſure
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62197:10"/> ſuitable to his infinite Perfection, the Manifeſtation would oppreſs and confound us. Our greateſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Powers could not bear ſuch a Revelation. But at the Reſurrection we ſhall be like unto the Angles, endow'd with ſuch vaſt extent of Capacity, as may fit us to entertain thoſe diſcoveries of the eternal Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which ſhall be the inconceivable fruition of the ſtate of Immortality. And this may ſuffice to ſhew (though in a very imperfect manner) the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude, which the Children of the Reſurrection have unto the Angles.</p>
            <p>III. There remains another inſtance of their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in that happy Condition, namely, their reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance even to God himſelf, which is delivered in theſe terms, <hi>They are the Children of God.</hi> There is no remainder of thoſe frail and periſhing Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in them, which they derived from their Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Parents.</p>
            <p>It is uſual in the Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſtyle them, who by Faith and Repentance are born again, the Children of God. Thus Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 3. 26. <hi>Ye are all the Children of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And this Relation creates in us a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to our Heavenly Father: Our Souls carry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 15.</note> Lineaments. It makes us <hi>holy, as He is holy.</hi> But certainly our Saviour (in the Text) intended more, when he makes it a principal part of Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bliſs, that we are then <hi>the Children of God.</hi> We ſhall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62197:10"/> then be more eminently; more reſemblingly ſo. If Grace render us like him here, Glory ſhall much more there. His Image in us ſhall be infinitely more expreſs, our likeneſs to him more exact. For every thing, which in this Life gives us a reſemblance to God, ſhall then be raiſed to Perfection; we ſhall then attain unto <hi>fulneſs of Stature.</hi> And theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Lines, and firſt Draughts upon the Soul, ſhall be fill'd up and finiſh't, in that bleſſed ſtate of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. But in what inſtances, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner this ſhall be, is not for me to deſcribe. For S. <hi>John</hi> himſelf leaves it to future Manifeſtation. 1 Joh. 3. 2. <hi>Beloved, now we are the Sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be: But we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> For the preſent, moſt ſure it is, that we are the Sons of God: But how much more perfectly we ſhall be ſo at the Reſurrection, is not revealed as yet. Only in general, we ſhall be like unto God: otherwiſe it would be impoſſible for us to ſuſtain the beatific Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to ſee him as he is, or to enjoy that Bleſſedneſs which he will then impart to us. But no words are ſignificant enough to give any tollerable account of this happy Future State; which is as unknown to us, as the offices and entertainments of Life are to the Child in the Womb, till our Powers and Capacities are come to their perfection. And thus I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to explain the Inſtances, which the Text
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62197:11"/> gives of the Glory we ſhall obtain in the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Neither can they die any more; for they are equal unto the Angles, and are the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſideration whereof does certainly afford us the moſt powerful and effectual Conſolation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all the Miſeries of Humane Life. For we can ſuffer nothing here, that can bear the loweſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Retributions of another World, when we ſhall become Immortal, Angelical, and even the Children of God in Glory. This was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, Rom. 8. 16, 17, 18. <hi>The Spirit it ſelf bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth witneſs with our ſpirit, that we are the Children of God. And if Children, then Heirs, Heirs of God, and Joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs with Chirſt: If ſo be that we ſuffer with him, that we may be alſo glorified together. For I reckon that the Sufferings of this preſent Time, are not worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Glory which ſhall be revealed in us.</hi> This Apoſtle's determination, though expreſt in general terms, holds true in all particulars. For example: We want Health it may be: our Bodies are full of Pains and Languiſhment: our Days are uneaſie; and our Nights reſtleſs; the moſt orderly Regiment of our ſelves, and all the aids of the Phyſician, can ſcarce preſerve us in that ſickly life we enjoy: But here is our Comfort, that in the Reſurrection we ſhall be freed from theſe tormenting Sorrows: <hi>This Mortal ſhall put on Immortality.</hi> And though in this Tabernacle of the Body, we do groan, being bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62197:11"/> with various and diſquieting Maladies, yet the time is coming, when <hi>Mortality ſhall be ſwallowed up of Life,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 4. Perhaps we are reduced to Poverty, and put to ſuffer the difficult Incumbrances of a needy condition: In which (as is uſual) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Friends forſake us; and we have the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional ſorrow of finding our ſelves Deſpiſed and become Ridiculous. But ſtill let us ſupport our ſelves with the meditation of Heavenly Treaſures laid up for us. So did thoſe Ancient Chriſtians, <hi>Heb. 10. 34. They took joyfully the ſpoiling of their Goods, knowing in themſelves that they had in Heaven a better and an enduring Subſtance:</hi> exempted from Moth and Ruſt, and from Thieves; from Decay and from Violence. Our lot perchance is to undergo the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of Perſecution, branded with Characters of Infamy: <hi>Made as the Filth of the World, and the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of all things,</hi> and uſed accordingly. But all this is abundantly recompenſed in this Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that in the Reſurrection we ſhall be owned and avouched as the Children of God. Whereupon our Lord himſelf exhorts us thus, <hi>Rejoyce, and be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glad, for great is your reward in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5. 12. Death, it may be, makes breaches upon us, in our Families, or Friends. Firſt one falls, and then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and ſcarce have we gotten over the Grief of one Funeral, but a ſecond calls us to the ſame ſad Offices. And theſe alarms of Mortality, put us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62197:12"/> expectations of our own Diſſolution. Theſe are black and melancholic Contemplations, till we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think our ſelves that in the other World, they and we cannot die any more; and though we undergo a ſhort ſeparation, we ſhall meet again at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and enjoy a Heavenly Reunion, which ſhall never be interrupted, or embitter'd, much leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved. It is no doubt an unreaſonable Impoſition upon the gentleneſs of Humane Nature, to forbid thoſe tender expreſſions of Sorrow which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon over the Hearſes of our Relations and Friends. But 'tis withal a mighty alleviation of our Grief, when we have good reaſon to believe they died in the Favour and Love of God: That the Angels attended and conducted their departed Souls to their heavenly Reſt; that they are now out of the danger of Temptation, and having finiſht their Courſe, are gone to receive the Crown. Methinks in the midſt of our Lamentations, we ſhould not forbear even to rejoyce, and gratulate the happineſs of thoſe dear Souls, who are poſſeſt of that, which above all other things we moſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately deſired they might attain.</p>
            <p>In a word: When we have ſurvey'd all the Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Troubles, which in this frail and mortal Life we are ſubject to, though 'tis impoſſible to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their having ſome troubleſome impreſſions upon our Spirits, yet there are ſuch infinite Comforts to be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62197:12"/> derived from the conſideration of the future ſtate of the Bleſſed, as are ſufficient to enable us not only to endure, but to <hi>glory in Tribulations:</hi> as knowing that <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 3.</note> thereby Grace is promoted, and our Glory enhanced. All the Sufferings which the moſt Afflicted Man can undergo in this Life, are not to be mention'd in compariſon with the Joys and Glories of the Life to come; which St. <hi>Paul</hi> has expreſt in words of ſtrange <hi>emphaſis</hi> and ſignification: 2 <hi>Cor. 4. 17. For our light Affliction, which is but for a moment, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for us a far more exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe things cannot be underſtood till they are enjoyed. Even this Excellent Lady (whoſe Funerals have given occaſion to this Diſcourſe) in her higheſt, and moſt raviſhing Meditations of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, could but conjecture only, and that very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly, what God hath prepared for her, and for all thoſe that love him. But ſhe underſtood and felt ſo much, as ſerved to engage and animate her in all the Exerciſes of holy Living. And ſhe never thought thoſe Conditions hard, which God requires to <hi>make</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>us meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi> And this I ſhall endeavour to make appear in the following accounts of her; which I have col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected from the happy opportunities I have had for many Years, to make obſervation of her holy Life, and from ſome Memorials, which thoſe who beſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62197:13"/> knew her, have communicated to me. And if any can be ſo invidious, as to think the Character I ſhall give, can exceed the Subject, I ſhall ſay nothing, but that of the admirable <hi>Pliny: That thoſe that neglect the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. Epiſt. 21.</note> 
               <hi>doing Praiſe-worthy things, look upon all Commendation to Flattery.</hi> Nor ſhall I fear any Miſconſtructions, it being an excellent ſervice to Vertue and Piety, when thoſe Perſons who have been the greateſt Examples of it, are commended to Imitation. For an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sermons and Advices of Religion are not ſo perſuaſive, as a ſingle Example, eſpecially ſo Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious an one, as this moſt incomparable Perſon was.</p>
            <p>She was Born within few miles of this Place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fifth Daughter of her great and Vertuous Parents, of whoſe Blood and Deſcent, it is not my deſign to give any Account. Nor can it be needful to any, that have the leaſt acquaintance with the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory or Heraldry of the Kingdom. She was educated under the Care, Precepts, and Examples of her Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Mother: And her great and capacious Soul received and improved thoſe happy Advantages to ſuch a Degree, that (beſides other Qualifications proper to a Perſon of her Age, Sex, and Quality) ſhe had very early attained to great meaſures of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and of grave and wiſe Conduct; and (in the Prophets words) <hi>The Child was an Hundred Years</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Iſa. 65. 20.</note> 
               <hi>old.</hi> And this was no defect of Wit or Spirit. Her
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62197:13"/> compoſedneſs of Mind proceeded not from Phlegm: Nor was Dulneſs excuſed and concealed under the name of Gravity. She underſtood well, and (in its proper ſeaſon) could entertain her ſelf and others with all the innocent Ingenuities, and ſprightlineſs of Converſation. But her great Soul aſpired to more ſuitable Entertainments, to things Solid, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, and Rational. She had then ſo little of the Levity, Heats, and Indiſcretions common in that time of Life, that ſhe became Example to her Sex, even in her very young Years; and had thereby the mighty advantages of ſetting out at firſt in a right Courſe, gaining habits of Vertue, and exalting her Mind with the nobleſt Images and Rules of it.</p>
            <p>To the gaining theſe Attainments, ſhe had the aſſiſtance of a quick and ſharp Underſtanding, and deep Apprehenſion, with a Judgment ſo deſcerning, as happily determined her the right Way, when ſhe was at any time to conclude what was True or Falſe, Good or Evil. For having ſubmitted her innocent and unprejudiced Soul to the conduct of Vertue, and continually begging of Almighty God the Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Guidance of the Holy Spirit; ſhe was by this means preſerved from thoſe Errors, into which Pride and Confidence have ſeduced many others. Nor was it an inconſiderable Safeguard, that ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had upon her Spirit ſo great a ſenſe of Honour. By which I mean not any immoderate remembrance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62197:14"/> of her noble Extraction, nor any inſolent or haughty Behaviour towards others (for none could be more Humble and Obliging); but I mean a continual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to things naturally Great and Honourable, a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection to avoid all that is baſe and vile, and unſuitable to the dignity of Nature, and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Vertue, and to that conditon of Men from whom the Laws and Rules of Demeanour are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>Her Paſſions and Affections (as is uſual in the moſt elevated Souls) were great and quick: but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch admirable reſtraint and command, that one would have thought it had been Conſtitution in her, and not Diſcipline: And that ſhe had been the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of her Paſſions by the benevolence of Nature, and not by Care and Labour. But this latter was manifeſt. For ſhe was far from being inſenſible: And as ſhe underſtood as well as any, all the Offices of Friendſhip; ſo would her generous Mind reſent them. She had none of that Meanneſs in her, to ſtudy Diminutions of any Act of Kindneſs, or to ſuſpect a Deſign in it; but magnify'd it to others, and to her ſelf too. She readily ſuppoſed every thing that could greaten the Teſtimonies of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to her; and her Recompences always bore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to this Generoſity. She was always jealous her Returns had not been ſufficient, and that ſhe had come ſhort of the juſt performances of a Friend.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:62197:14"/>
            <p>But in caſe of any neglect or failure towards her, of any unkindneſs or diſſervice (in what meaſure ſoever ſhe might apprehend it) all her Reſentments were ſealed up. Not that ſhe kept any black Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Injuries, or Memento's againſt an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Retaliation: But ſhe conſider'd all that could leſſen the Offence, and where it could not be defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe made ſure to forgive it. And if any expreſt a concernment that ſhe was Injured, ſhe labour'd to appeaſe them, by alleging all imaginable Excuſes and Extenuations of the Offender's Fault: Not eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any intereſt of her own worthy the paſſion of a Friend's Vindication.</p>
            <p>She bore ſo perfect a hatred to all Vice and Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, that the leaſt approaches towards it in any Perſon, received from her the reprehenſion of a Bluſh, or a Frown, of (if ſhe judg'd it expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) a more direct and open Confutation. But ſhe had few occaſions to exerciſe this part of her Vertue: For her preſence was awful; and 'tis a Torment to vain and extravagant Perſons, to be under the Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Confinement which Vertuous Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny puts upon them. It is poſſible nevertheleſs, that in many Perſons far inferiour to her in Goodneſs, ſome actions and behaviours of a reſembling Nature may be obſerved. But then they are commonly but the Oſtentations of a counterfeit Vertue; little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and ambuſhes to get Fame and Commendation.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62197:15"/> In her they were grown to Cuſtom: So Habitual and Familiar, that ſhe never expected any Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ought to be made of them.</p>
            <p>To all theſe Qualities of a cultivated and enlarg'd Mind, excellent Underſtanding, and a commanding Reaſon, ſhe ſupperadded a Holy, Pure, and even Angelical Life. To know God, and to be like him, was her firſt and great Endeavour. She lived al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in proſpect of Heaven, and thither did her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Spirit evermore aſpire. This made thoſe Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which prevail ſo fatally upon others, prove only Moleſtations to her. This World (as it was to <hi>Monica,</hi> diſcourſing of Heaven with her holy Son), <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſt. Conf. ſ.</hi> 9. c. 10.</note> was vile and diſpicable in her Eye, whoſe Contemplations and Longings, were directed to things Eternal. She wiſely concluded, that a meek and quiet Spirit, a true Devotion and ſevere Vertue, were more excellent Acquiſitions, and more lovely Ornaments, than any of the gaudy Vanities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with vulgar and narrow Souls are ſo unreaſonably tranſported. Nor did ſhe only approve the things that are Excellent, but ſhe practiſed them alſo, to ſuch a Degree, that in her, Primitive Chriſtianity was revived; and ſhe lived as thoſe firſt Chriſtians did, and as we ſhould. And this (by the Grace of God) preſerved her from thoſe low conceptions of Religion, which many have taken up: Who would make it to conſiſt in the little badges and cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizances
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62197:15"/> of a Party; in angry Diſputings, and fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Wranglings; in bringing all things into Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and projecting eternal amendments in Spiritual Affairs; in zealous contending about Words and Names, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Talk and Pretence ſhe never eſteem'd worthy her Conſideration; and was not to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon by the ſleights and oſtentation of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors for other Churches. But having upon Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Judgment and Conviction, fully ſatisfy'd her ſelf, ſhe conſcienciouſly and devoutly adhered to the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And though (like <hi>Mary</hi> in in the Goſpel) ſhe had thus <hi>choſen the better part,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Religion her great Buſineſs and Employment; yet ſhe was ſenſibly offended when ſhe found it taken notice of, unleſs it were by Imitation. Her deſign being to provoke others to good Works, not to flattering Attributions. Not that ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of being thought Religious, but ſhe dreaded the Hypocriſy of a deſigned Publication that ſhe was ſo.</p>
            <p>And as a further Evidence that ſhe ſtudied the Power of Godlineſs, not the Form of it, ſhe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd moſt in the retired intimacies of true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This appear'd in the conſtant frequency of her private Devotions, which ſhe perform'd three times a Day at the leaſt: Uſing to that purpoſe the moſt private Concealments, not only to avoid Diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62197:16"/> but (what ſhe more ſhun'd) Diſcovery. And to aſſiſt, enlarge, and enforce her Devotions, ſhe added to them frequent Faſts. Wherein ſhe held her ſelf to our Saviour's Rule, <hi>Mat. 6. 16. When ye Faſt, be not as the Hypocrites, of a ſad Countenance: For they disfigure their Faces, that they may appear unto Men to Faſt. But when thou faſteſt, anoint thy Head, and waſh thy Face, that thou appear not unto Men to Faſt, but unto thy Father, which is in ſecret; and thy Father, which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall reward thee openly.</hi> Thus upon ſuch occaſions, ſhe would ſeem to eat, and to take her uſual Repaſt, that ſhe might eſcape Obſervation: Nor would any thing more diſcompoſe her, than an inquiſition into her Abſtinence.</p>
            <p>To her Prayers and Faſting, ſhe added (as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Concomitant) Alms to the Poor, in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whereof ſhe was extermely Kind and Bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and was ſomewhat ſevere to her ſelf oftentimes, that ſhe might be the more Charitable to them that were in Need. And her Liberality in this kind was always accompanied with ſuch a condeſcending and obliging Compaſſion, as render'd her Reliefs of the Diſtreſſed doubly comforting to them. But in theſe Pious Diſtributions ſhe uſed ſuch means of ſecrecy, that no more particular accounts can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than ſuch as can be gathered from thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who to manifeſt their Gratitude, have made treſpaſs upon their promiſes of Concealment.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:62197:16"/>
            <p>To ſuſtain and nouriſh this conſtant courſe of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Devotion, ſhe drew daily Succours from the Holy Scriptures, beginning and concluding every Day with ſome Portion of them. And this not as a Task, and to maintain a Cuſtom, but as a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Delight, and the moſt agreable entertainment of her Mind. Which appeared in her Youthful time, when about Twenty Years ſince, ſhe reſided here in this Town, the Bell at Four in the Morning (even in the Winter Seaſon) was her certain Summons to her Devotions, which were ſeconded by diligent Reading and Meditating upon the holy Word of God. Wherein ſhe aſſiſted her ſelf, not only by Public Sermons, but by the beſt and ſoundeſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors, which our Church affords. And all this, not to give her ſelf a mere intellectual Improvement and Satisfaction. But ſhe ſuffer'd the Divine Law to paſs into Government: It ruled and commanded her in all her Actions; and ſhe adorned the Doctrine of God our Saviour, by a ſuitable Converſation.</p>
            <p>But it is not to be omitted, that the principal of all her Joys, was the bleſſed Sacrament. Her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Soul finding the moſt ſatisfying refreſhments in the Spiritual Feaſt of the moſt precious Body and Blood of her Saviour; which made her moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly embrace every Opportunity ſhe could lay hold on to partake of that holy Myſtery. Accordingly ſhe Communicated once every Month, ſince her
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62197:17"/> Reſidence in <hi>London;</hi> fitting her ſelf before-hand with all poſſible preparations due to the Dignity of that Divine Celebration. And herein ſhe exerciſed ſuch Acts of Devotion, and Religious Auſterity to her ſelf, as if it had been the laſt Act of her Life: And that ſhe were to paſs from the Altar to the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, from the Table of our Lord to his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Seat. Neither was this with the neglect of other Duties. For ſhe loved to draw nigh to God, in all the Ways of approaching him. She attended the Church upon all Occaſions, with a zeal like that of holy <hi>Anna,</hi> who <hi>departed not from the Temple, but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 27.</note> 
               <hi>ſerved God with Eaſtings and Prayers Night and Day.</hi> And ſo much was her Mind fixed upon the Offices of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that as ſoon as ever ſhe could obtain Releaſe from Buſineſs, or from Company, ſhe took up ſome work of Devotion, and return'd to thoſe Spiritual Fruitions, with new Appetites and impatient Deſires.</p>
            <p>Yet did not all this Retirement, and the Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Employments of it, contract any moroſeneſs of Humour in her. Herein ſhe alſo imitated her Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: Who though He ſpent whole Nights in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and lived as became the Son of God, and the Redeemer of the World; yet was pleaſed to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with infinite Benignity and Condeſcention, even to the meaneſt People. For her Religion was of ſuch a Complexion, that ſhe never lookt upon rigid Sowrneſs, and cenſorious Auſterity, to be any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62197:17"/> Ornament to it. The Holy Spirit (ſhe well knew) produces Fruits of another kind: Namely, <hi>Love, Joy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 22.</note> Which Fruits, all that had the happineſs to know her, will acknowledg were eminently viſible in her Life and Actions.</p>
            <p>Thus perpetually exerciſing upon her ſelf ſo wiſe and holy a Diſcipline, ſhe arrived to ſo noble an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Mind, that the aſſaults of Paſſion could not move her. For certainly none ever had a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evenneſs of Mind, and calmneſs of Spirit, in all Events. Some occaſions ſhe met with, that put to trial her Patience and Contentment: But in her they Produced no viſible alteration. She ſtill preſerved her wonted conſtancy and ſerenity of Soul. Not that ſhe was Inſenſible, but ſhe was Content. Her Philoſophy was not Stoical, but Chriſtian; it was not Apathy, but Reſignation.</p>
            <p>In ſhort: So uniform was ſhe in the practice of all Chriſtian Vertue, that ſhe adorned and illuſtrated every Relation wherein ſhe ſtood. A Friend ſhe was even to Supererogation, beyond what could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, or without Reluctancy (ſometimes) admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A moſt dutiful Daughter even to the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and Example. A Wife preciſely obſervant, from the ſmalleſt things to the greateſt, provident and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in all the Concernments of her worthy Husband; ſtudying and contriving his Intereſts and Satisfaction
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62197:18"/> in every thing. She was ſuch a Wife, in whom the <hi>Heart of her Husband did ſafely truſt:</hi> in whom he had <note place="margin">Pro. 31. 11.</note> all joy and delight. To which he made the moſt affectionate returns of Kindneſs, Love, and tendereſt Care. All which are now redoubled upon her little Daughter, the only pledg of their Conjugal Affection.</p>
            <p>For ſo it pleaſed Almighty God to order it, That in the midſt of this Excellent Ladie's preparation for Communicating at the Lord's Table, ſhe was ſeized with that Diſeaſe, which ſoon after became Mortal to her. On the next Lord's-Day in the Morning, ſhe thought her ſelf in condition to leave her Bed, and pay her Devotions at Church, and to partake of the holy Sacrament, that Day to be adminiſtred. But thoſe vigorous longings of her Soul, made her judge too well of the ſtate of her Body. For her ſtrength ſoon fail'd her: and they that attended her, found it neceſſary to continue her in all the accommodations of a Sick Person. And ſhe her ſelf alſo was (by this time) ſo far convinced of the weak condition of her Body, that ſhe concluded her End was near; and thenceforth diſmiſt all Worldly Thoughts and Cares, and every thing that might give Impediment to her in her preparations for another World. Then it was (when ſhe had before her the mighty proſpect of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity) that ſhe ſeverely Arraign'd and Judg'd her ſelf: examining her Life paſt with the ſtricteſt and moſt accurate ſcrutiny. What paſt between God and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62197:18"/> her own Soul, we cannot pretend to know. But ſhe diſcover'd a trouble, not without bemoaning her ſelf, That ſhe had not improved her time as ſhe ought to have done. If one that liv'd ſuch a holy and ſevere Life makes ſuch complaints, Good God! what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts will thoſe Perſons make, whoſe times is their burden, who call in Pleaſures, Vanity, Folly, and Vice, to drive it away.</p>
            <p>One thing more did (it ſeems) touch her Thoughts, which was this, That ſhe had ſet her Heart too much upon her little Child: So jealous was ſhe, leſt a juſt Natural Affection ſhould grow ſo immoderate, as to become Criminal, and her Love to God ſuffer any abatements by her kindneſs to an only Child. Self-accuſations of this ſort were indications of a very tender Conſcience, and of a very innocent Soul. Happy Saint! That upon her Death-bed had no greater matter againſt her ſelf. Who would not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſuch Peace as ſhe then felt, at any rate whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever? Her acquaintance with God, and her intereſt in Him, were not then to be made: That had been her early Care, and daily Buſineſs. Her Life came under continual reviews; and ſhe <hi>judg'd her ſelf,</hi> to prevent God's judging her. Her account was always in a readineſs to be deliver'd up: And her hopes of Heaven were ſo fixt and raviſhing, that the World could not tempt, nor Death affright her; but ſhe entertain'd her Diſſolution as her Privilege; and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62197:19"/> 
               <hi>(being Righteous) ſhe had hope in her Death,</hi> Prov. 14. 32.</p>
            <p>Nor was ant thing of this to be aſcribed to her Diſtemper. Sickneſs, 'tis true, does often ſtupify the Mind: and the oppreſſion of the Spirits may be ſometimes miſtaken for an undiſturbed and unſettled Soul. But in her 'twas manifeſtly the aſſurance of Faith, and Chriſtian confidence in the Merits and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of her dear Lord and Saviour. For God continu'd to her in all the time of her Sickneſs, the great mercy of a clear Underſtanding, and perfect Sence and Memory to the laſt: Which ſhe moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly made uſe of in humble Reſignations, devout Prayers, heavenly Meditations, holy Diſcourſes, and Advices, and in all ſuitable entertainments of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting Soul.</p>
            <p>At laſt, Without Agonies, or any great Pains, without frightful Accidents, without Fears and Horrors, without the diſturbance of Temptations: But in a ſweet Calm of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in ſtedfaſt Faith, and perfect Charity, in joyful expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Eternal Life, ſhe quietly gave up her Soul into the Hands of her moſt Merciful Redeemer.</p>
            <p>Thus liv'd, and thus dy'd this Excellent Perſon, in peace with God, in Communion with his Church, in Charity with all the World; leaving the Memorial and Example of her holy Life, to the Imitation of all that deſire to excel in Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. And though we mourn and lament her Death, let it not be, without the conſolation of this Remembrance, that <hi>She cannot die any more, but is equal with the Angels, and is a Child of God, being one of the Children of the Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62197:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
